בוקר טוב, Boker tov, welcome to the last day of פסח, Pesach,
the what feels like
the first day of summer.
Ninth day of the עומר. Omer. Okay, כ"ז עמוד ב', chaf zayin
amud bais, the משנה. Mishnah. המפריש חטאתו ומת לא יביאנה בנו תחתיו
Hamafrish chataso meys lo yevienu bno tachtov או אחר אחריו. or acharav.
So, תנא משנה, tana mishnah, thank you, כ"ז עמוד ב'. chaf zayin
amud bais. Somebody sets aside a חטאת chatas and then he dies,
his son cannot bring his father's חטאת. chatas. Okay, so now we're
getting into some very
specific rules about not when you are obligated, but of the use
of yesterday we did about how much it has to cost and
the use of the money. Now we're talking about the use of
one thing for another. So, you cannot the son cannot use his
father's חטאת, chatas, either for the father because the father is already
dead and there's no כפרה kapara for מתים, meysim,
all of our understandings about קדיש Kaddish and learning משניות Mishnayos and
whatever aside, but at least there's no formal halachic כפרה kapara for
מתים meysim and he can't use it for himself because you can't
use a חטאת chatas for the sinner or person it was not
designated
for. לא יביאנה מחטא על חטא, Lo yevienu mechait al chait, you
can't bring it and even the person himself can't bring it from
if he designated for one sin, he can't bring it for another
sin. אפילו הפריש על חלב שאכל אמש לא יביאנה על חלב שאכל
היום, Afilu hifrish al chelev she'achal emesh lo yevienu al chelev she'achal
hayom, even if it's from if he set it aside for חלב
chelev that he ate yesterday he can't bring it for חלב chelev
today. So even from the exact same type of sin, but it
cannot be for a different act. A חטאת chatas is specifically designated
for the person and for the sin.
שנאמר קרבנו על חטאתו, Shene'emar korbano al chataso, it says when he
brings his קרבן korban for his sin. אשר חטא, Asher chata, his
קרבנו, korbano, his חטאתו, chataso, not his father's חטאתו chataso and משום
חטאתו mishum chataso for his sin, not for the specific sin, not
for a different sin that it was designated for. גמרא, Gemara, yes,
we really can't ask too many questions today, we have lots to
cover, yes. Okay, fine.
What's the פסוק? pasuk? ויקרא, Vayikra, there you
go, think about. מנא הני מילי, Minani mili, where do we know
this from? תנו רבנן, Tanu rabbanan, קרבנו, korbano, his sin. Now it
says קרבנו korbano a lot of times when it speaks about bringing
a קרבן. korban. Okay,
רש"י Rashi says by the way, it says let's see by עולה
ויורד olah veyored it says מחטאתו. mechataso. No, that's a different point.
Okay, anyway, looking in the wrong רש"י. Rashi. Anyway, okay, קרבנו, korbano,
his sin. מנא הני מילי דתנו רבנן קרבנו, Minani mili detanu rabbanan
korbano, וקרבנו הוא יוצא ואינו יוצא בקרבן אביו. vekorbano hu yotzei ve'eino
yotzei bekorban aviv. His קרבן, korban, not his father's קרבן. korban. יכול
לא יצא בקרבן
אביו בהמה שהפריש אביו מן הקלה על החמורה. Yachol lo yetzei bekorban
aviv behema shehifrish aviv min hakala al hachamura. Maybe you can't use
it for a sin that the dad set aside for a lighter
sin if he has a more weightier sin. Let's say his father
set aside for a sin of כרת kares and he's bringing it
for a sin that's חייב מיתה. chayav misa. או מן החמורה על
הקלה, O min hachamura al hakala,
or maybe even if it's from a weightier for a lighter, but
still there's different genres of sin. אבל יוצא בקרבן שהפריש אביו מן
הקלה על הקלה מן החמורה על החמורה. Aval yotzei bekorban shehifrish aviv
min hakala al hakala min hachamura al hachamura. If it's the same
type of weight of sin that his father set aside for a
כרת kares maybe he can use it for a כרת, kares, or
for מיתה misa he can use it for a מיתה? misa? תלמוד
לומר קרבנו. Talmud lomar korbano. No, nevertheless the פסוק pasuk still says
קרבנו. korbano. בקרבנו
הוא יוצא ואינו יוצא בקרבנו של אביו. Bekorbano hu yotzei ve'eino yotzei
bekorbano shel aviv. Only your קרבן, korban, only the person's קרבן, korban,
not his father's קרבן. korban. The חטאת chatas works only for the
person who set it aside for his use. Okay, now, יכול לא
יצא בקרבן אביו בהמה שהפריש אפילו מן הקלה על הקלה מן החמורה
על החמורה. Yachol lo yetzei bekorban aviv behema shehifrish afilu min hakala
al hakala min hachamura al hachamura. Fine, a person can't use his
father's קרבן korban for something even if it's the same weight of
sin, light or heavy, he can't use his father's for his sin.
שהרי אינו מגלח על נזירותו בבהמה שהפריש אביו, Sheharei eino megalach al
neziruso behema shehifrish aviv, because we already have a precedent for that
idea. If his father set aside an animal for to be used
as a for a קרבן korban of a נזיר nazir and then
the son decided to become a נזיר, nazir, he cannot use his
father's קרבן. korban. We already know that. Okay, so that already is
like we'll take that for granted. So this follows that pattern. אבל,
Aval, but maybe I should suggest יוצא בדמים שהפריש אביו ואפילו מן
הקלה על החמורה מן החמורה על הקלה. yotzei bidamos shehifrish aviv va'afilu
min hakala al hachamura min hachamura al hakala. Let's say his father
did set aside an animal, let's say his father only set aside
money, sanctified money for the use of a חטאת, chatas, actually sanctified,
not just set aside. So there maybe he can use the money
his father sanctified for his father's חטאת chatas and now his father's
dead. Maybe he can use it for his. Why should I think
that should be different? שהרי, Sheharei,
because by parallel by the נזיר nazir case actually that does work.
We have a הלכה halacha that אדם מגלח על נזירותו על דמים
שהפריש אביו adam megalach al neziruso al damos shehifrish aviv בזמן שהם
סתומים ולא בזמן שהם מפורשים. bizman sheheim stumin velo bizman sheheim meforashin.
That if his father sets aside money for נזירות nezirus and he
didn't say which of the money's going to be used for a
חטאת, chatas, which is going to be used for an עולה, olah,
they're סתומים, stumin, they're not מפורשים. meforashin. He just set aside a
pile of money, this money is for my נזירות, nezirus, then we
actually have a הלכה halacha again we're not going to get into
where we know it from, we'll learn מסכת נזיר Masechet Nazir we'll
talk about it, but we have a הלכה halacha that the son
can use that money for the son's נזירות. nezirus. So if by
סברה, sevara,
yes, it doesn't matter, I'm pretty sure. Okay, so anyway, so therefore
if we have a precedent that money the father set aside under
some circumstances can be used for the son, maybe the same should
work here. תלמוד לומר קרבנו. Talmud lomar korbano. No, nevertheless the פסוק
pasuk still says קרבנו. korbano. וקרבנו הוא יוצא ואינו יוצא בקרבן אביו.
Vekorbano hu yotzei ve'eino yotzei bekorban aviv. Only the person can only
use his own. Even if it's a case that in parallel would
work by נזירות. nezirus.
Fine, I get you that he can't use his father's money even
if it's just money and even if it's just from light to
light, the same genre, אבל יוצא בקרבן שהפריש לעצמו. aval yotei be-korban
she-hifrish le-atzmo.
Put aside the father. Fine, that's not his קרבן. korban. But maybe
if it's a קרבן korban he set aside for himself for one
sin, maybe he can use it for another sin, אפילו מן החמור
על הקל ומן הקל על החמור, afilu min ha-chamur al ha-kal u-min
ha-kal al ha-chamur, maybe even if it's from different types, heavy to
light or light to heavy, but if it's his own קרבן korban
maybe he can switch the designation. תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar קרבנו על
חטאתו. korbano al chatato.
It says his קרבן korban for his sin. So not only is
it his קרבן, korban, it's his sin. The sin has to also
be the same sin it was designated for, עד שיהיה לשם חטאת
ad she-yehei le-shem chatat or חטאתו chatato possibly,
until it is for the sake of the sin that he designated
it for, you cannot switch its designation. יכול לא יצא בקרבנו ומה
שהפריש לעצמו אפילו
מן הקל על הקל
ומן החמור על החמור.
Yachol lo yeitzei be-korbano u-ma she-hifrish le-atzmo afilu min ha-kal al
ha-kal u-min ha-chamur al ha-chamur.
I get that you cannot use a קרבן korban for yourself even
if you're switching it within like things, light to light, heavy to
heavy, it's your own קרבן, korban, nevertheless you can't switch the designation.
שכן אם הפריש בהמה על חלב והביא על דם, על דם והביא
על חלב. she-ken im hifrish behema al cheilev ve-heivi al dam, al
dam ve-heivi al cheilev. That makes sense that you can't go ahead
and use something that you set aside for blood for fat or
for fat for blood. Why does that make sense? שהרי לא מעל
ולא כיפר. she-harei lo ma'al ve-lo kiper. That if you were to
let's say have set aside... just let me just double check one
thing...
yeah, hold on one minute...
right. So the word לא מעל lo ma'al does not literally mean
לא מעל. lo ma'al. What it means is is that if you
set aside, we're going to learn soon in מעילה, Meilah, that when
you have a קרבן korban or a כלי שרת, kli shareis, you
then if even if you are מועל, moel, you misuse it and
take it for yourself, it does not go out לחולין. le-chullin. When
you're dealing with things that are more owned, not קדושת הגוף, kedushat
ha-guf, but more קדושת, kedushat, you know דמים, damim, they're owned as
property by the בית המקדש, Beis ha-Mikdash, then if you're מועל moel
they do go out לחולין. le-chullin. When you steal them, not only
have you transgressed or whatever, they lose their קדושה, kedusha, they become
חולין. chullin. So here it's saying like this. I get that you
cannot redesignate a קרבן korban you've set aside for one purpose for
the other because that identity, here's conceptually what it's saying, that identity
is fixed. That identity doesn't change. The evidence to that is that
even if you were to try to do מעילה meilah by this
animal, it would not lose its קדושה. kedusha. Its identity is absolutely
fixed and rigid and therefore you can't switch it from one thing
to another. But let's say you didn't set aside an animal. Let's
say you set aside money. Now if you did מעילה meilah with
that money, the קדושה kedusha would go away. Since therefore the קדושה
kedusha could leave this money, the identity therefore is not as fixed
and as absolute. And therefore maybe you are in a position to
redesignate it. Okay, and therefore... so that's the question. Maybe it's easier
to redesignate money than redesignate an animal because by the animal the
קדושה kedusha is more fixed, it doesn't change even if you do
מעילה. meilah. Another thing could have pointed out is if the animal
doesn't have a blemish... you can't redeem an animal without a blemish,
you can't remove the קדושה, kedusha, but if it's money you can
transfer the קדושה. kedusha. So that's another evidence that the קדושה kedusha
is more fixed with an animal than it is with money. So
let's read that again.
So
שכן אם הפריש בהמה על חלב והביא על דם, על דם והביא
על חלב, she-ken im hifrish behema al cheilev ve-heivi al dam, al
dam ve-heivi al cheilev, that would not work. Why? שהרי לא מעל
ולא כיפר. she-harei lo ma'al ve-lo kiper. Since you would not do
מעילה... meilah... it doesn't really mean you would do מעילה, meilah, but
if you do מעילה meilah it would not take the money out
לחולין. le-chullin. Therefore you cannot atone for some other purpose. אבל יוצא
במעות שהפריש לעצמו מן הקל על הקל מן החמור על החמור. Aval
yotei be-ma'os she-hifrish le-atzmo min ha-kal al ha-kal u-min ha-chamur al ha-chamur.
Maybe if it's just money that's designated for a חטאת, chatas, maybe
you can redesignate it. או מן הדם והביא על החלב o min
ha-dam ve-heivi al ha-cheilev or maybe even, you know, I skipped a
line, או מן החמור על הקל ומן הקל על החמור. o min
ha-chamur al ha-kal u-min ha-kal al ha-chamur. Maybe even if it's different
genres, maybe even not the same genre. Maybe if it's just money
you can redesignate it for a different type of a sin, even
a more weighty or lighter one. שכן אם הפריש לעצמו מעות על
החלב. she-ken im hifrish le-atzmo ma'os al ha-cheilev.
Let's say you set aside money for yourself to bring for a
קרבן חלב korban cheilev והביא על הדם ve-heivi al ha-dam
and you chose to go ahead and say, you know what, I'm
just going to take that money and use it for a different
קרבן, korban, for דם, dam, for חטאת, chatas, which is exactly what
we're asking you should be allowed to do. But even if you
weren't allowed to do it, על הדם והביא על החלב al ha-dam
ve-heivi al ha-cheilev or for the דם dam you brought for the
חלב, cheilev, which is exactly what we're asking should you be allowed
to do that, but it's saying let's imagine you weren't allowed to
do that. What would be the הלכה halacha in that case? שהרי
מעל וכיפר. she-harei ma'al ve-kiper. Even if it didn't work, what would
happen? You would have taken the money away from חלב, cheilev, you
would have been עובר over on מעילה, meilah, the money would have
become desanctified,
you would have then used it for דם, dam, you therefore would
have been using your own money for דם dam because now the
money was desanctified once you transgressed מעילה, meilah, and it would have
worked, you would have been able to bring that קרבן. korban. So
since were you to have transgressed מעילה meilah if we're dealing with
money, actually it would have worked to reuse it with you having
transgressed, but that proves that it's a possibility.
Maybe this money can switch its designation because you see in theory
that could happen.
Even though we say you're over, so you're allowed?
No, no, but since even if you weren't allowed to, it would
work, maybe that should be evidence that that's a possibility
and re-assignment is possible and once it's possible, maybe you should even
be allowed to do it. Okay, since we know anyway it would
work, so therefore maybe that will work. תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar קרבנו
על חטאתו. korbano al hatato. Your sin on your קרבן. korban. It
has to be fixed and cannot be switched. עד שיהא קרבנו לשם
חטאתו. Ad sheyehe korbano leshem hatato. Your קרבן, korban, not your father's,
your sin, not a different sin, even if it's just money, even
if it's not the animal. Now, מאי לומר ולא כיפר? mai lomar
velo kiper? What does it mean in the first case if you
tried to reuse your
animal from one thing to another, from blood to חלב cheilev or
vice versa, you would not have been מועל mo'el and therefore you
would not have atoned? תגני בהשם ובאשם קמיה דרב פפא, Tagni b'Hashem
uv'Asham kammei d'Rav Pappa, הכי קאמר: hachi ka'amar: this is what it
means. כיון דלא מצי מעל, Keivan d'lo matzi maal, since you can't
do מעילה, me'ilah, doesn't mean you can't do מעילה, me'ilah, but it
means that your מעילה me'ilah will not take the money out to
חולין, chullin, so therefore כיפורי נמי לא מכפר. kippurei nami lo mechaper.
Obviously you won't be able to use it for the different one,
because this designation is obviously fixed and cannot change. הואיל וכך לא
מצי משני. Ho'il v'chach lo matzi meshanei. Since there is no way
even by transgressing that you could use this animal for something else
because it would never go out to חולין, chullin, so because there's
no way even through transgression it'll work, you're not entitled to switch
its designation. אבל מעות, Aval maot, but when you're dealing with money,
כיון דאי משני מעל ומייתי קרבן מעילה. keivan d'ee meshani maal umayti
korban me'ilah. So if you were to actually... assuming it didn't work,
even if it were not allowed to do it, what would be
the הלכה? halachah? You would have transgressed, you'd have to bring a
קרבן korban for transgressing מעילה, me'ilah, but the money would have been
gone out to חולין chullin and then would have achieved getting the
other קרבן korban and you would have actually got atonement for the
other קרבן korban that you brought. So since it actually could work
even though it would work with transgression, maybe since it could work,
it should be allowed to work? אימא מתחילה נמי מייתי. Eima mitchilah
nami mayti. Maybe even לכתחילה lechatchilah you should be allowed to redesignate
because by the money its designation is not as fixed as by
the בהמה. behemah. קא משמע לן Ka mashma lan that you're not.
If you want to do מעילה, me'ilah, go ahead... I mean obviously
you're not allowed, and then you transgress and it would work. But
you are not entitled to reassign it. The identity is fixed. And
this of course is what we've been saying all along by a
חטאת, chatas, you know that a חטאת chatas is specific to the
person, to the sin. The משנה mishnah is clear even from one
sin of חלב cheilev to another sin of חלב cheilev and so
on. There's a little bit of a question about by אשם תלוי,
asham talui, since that's a little bit more about the person, a
little less about the sin. There is an opinion that even from
חלב cheilev to דם dam or whatever it could work. In the
end we פוסקין pasken that אשם תלוי asham talui follows the rules
of a חטאת. chatas.
Okay, that is that הלכה. halachah.
And that has to be
ראשונים, rishonim, right?
Something like that.
Well, a שלמים shlamim is not specific to a sin, so I'm
not sure that...
No, like a... you know, this קרבן korban I'm going to do
מנזיר.
manazir. Okay, be a נזיר, nazir, okay? But basically שלמים shlamim or
עולה, olah, if the father dies, the son could bring the שלמים
shlamim or the עולה olah the father said.
About a תודה? todah?
That's a good question. I'm pretty sure the הלכה halachah there is...
I mean even though it's true that a תודה todah is for
a specific thing of הודאה, hoda'ah, I don't think that its identity
is... I mean if... yeah, I'm 99% sure that if the father
dies, the son could bring
the תודה. todah. Why? Because the הלכה halachah is that not... you
know, is that the idea, ארבעה מביאין תודה arba'ah mevi'in todah and
so on...
it's not really...
there's never really a per se... I mean,
you know, there's never... it's more like... okay, I have to double
check, but from what I remember, it's not like there's a per
se חיוב chiyuv of a תודה. todah. Meaning, we do say that
in the four circumstances a person is supposed to bring a תודה
todah and so on, but it's nothing at all like the idea
of a חטאת. chatas. In the end of the day, you could
bring a תודה todah even if those circumstances didn't happen to you.
If those circumstances did happen to you and you didn't bring a
תודה, todah, I don't think... it's not like you'd be עובר over
for example on בל תאחר bal te'acher or something. I can double
check that, but in the end of the day, the תודה todah
is more a form of a שלמים shlamim than a real חיוב.
chiyuv. Alright, anyway, let's go on. מביאין מהקדש כשבה שעירה. Mevi'in me'hekdesh
kesevah se'irah. Now we're going to talk about what happens if you
set aside money and you're not redesignating it to a different sin,
but you are switching the object, the thing you're bringing for a
קרבן. korban. Now how could that be? Well, if a normal חטאת
chatas you only have it's either a sheep or a goat. So
that's also the question: you set aside the money, you're planning on
buying a sheep, can you now choose to buy a goat? Yes.
But the more interesting case is an עולה ויורד. oleh ve'yored. You'll
remember an עולה ויורד oleh ve'yored is a very small number of
sins where based on your economic standing you bring either a sheep
or a goat, or you bring two birds, one for חטאת, chatas,
one for עולה, olah, or you bring a מנחה. minchah. So there
what would happen if you set aside money for one and then
your financial standing shifted, could you then go ahead and use it
for the other thing? Not just from a sheep to a goat,
but really from one type of animal to a very different type
of animal. Let's take a look.
What does the משנה mishnah say?
Let's read the משנה. mishnah. מביאין מהקדש כשבה. Mevi'in me'hekdesh kesevah. מה
תנינא, Mah tanina, let's read the משנה. Mishnah. מביאין מהקדש כשב לשעירה.
mevi'in me'hekdesh kesev lise'irah. If you set aside money for a sheep,
you can go ahead and change your mind and use it for
a goat, even though we said you can't switch from one חטאת
Chatas to another, you can change your intention which animal you're going
to bring it for. It's not designated specifically for, it's not sheep
money, it's חטאת Chatas money, but not sheep money. ומהקדש שעירה לכשב,
u'mehekdesh se'irah l'kesev, or similarly if you set it aside for a
goat you can buy a sheep. ומהקדש כשב ושעירה, u'mehekdesh kesev u'se'irah,
if you set it aside for a sheep or goat and now
you got poorer and therefore it's an עולה ויורד, oleh ve'yored, this
is only in the very rare case of עולה ויורד, oleh ve'yored,
so now you're not forced to buy a sheep and a goat.
What can you do? You can bring תורין ובני ינה. torim u'vnei
yonah. You can use from that money to bring the turtle doves
or the pigeons instead. Now what does that mean? They're going to
cost a tenth or whatever it is, a fiftieth of the original
cost. You have to buy turtle doves and pigeons for a thousand
dollars? So no, the הלכה halacha is, רש״י Rashi is a little
interesting. רש״י Rashi says you take the money that you need for
the turtle doves and the pigeons and the rest becomes חולין. chullin.
That's what רש״י Rashi sounds like, which is a bizarre idea. How
did the money all of a sudden become חולין? chullin? The רמב״ם
Rambam says it differently. The רמב״ם Rambam says, or at least that's
what רש״י Rashi sounds like, it's not so clear, but the רמב״ם
Rambam says is you have your thousand dollars you set aside for
your sheep or however much, you buy your turtle doves for twenty
bucks and then what you do is you say, you buy it
with your own money and then you say the קדושה kedusha of
this thousand dollars is transferred onto the turtle doves or the pigeons.
Now we know that when you transfer קדושה kedusha from you're not
allowed generally to transfer קדושה kedusha of something of greater value to
lesser value, but if you do, it works. So you've totally removed
the קדושה kedusha from the thousand dollars, it's now on the turtle
doves and pigeons. And here what the משנה Mishnah is telling you
is you're allowed to do that because this is all for the
same קרבן, korban, your financial standing has shifted, so now your obligation
is not the sheep or the goat, it is the turtle doves.
Here even לכתחילה l'chatchila you are allowed to transfer the קדושה kedusha
and therefore you will have the rest of the money to spend
on your own personal needs. Yeah.
That is the way I always conceptualize it is, you know, at
the time you sinned whatever, you had a thousand dollars in your
bank account.
Now, you know, okay, so we're going to talk about that in
the גמרא, Gemara, when you determine your financial standing. Let's keep on
going. ומהקדש תורין ובני יונה לעשירית האיפה, u'mehekdesh torin u'vnei yonah l'asiris
ha'eifah, and similarly if you set aside the money for pigeons and
turtle doves and now you became even poorer, you can transfer that
קדושה kedusha for the purposes of the מנחה mincha and any difference
you can pocket.
Okay. So where were we? ובני יונה, u'vnei yonah, עשירית האיפה, asiris
ha'eifah, כיצד, keitzad, how would this work?
הפריש כשב לשעירה העני, hifrish kesev lise'irah he'ani, and then you became
poorer after you set aside for the sheep or the goat, יביא
עוף, yavi of, then bring a bird and as I said pocket
the difference. העני, he'ani, you got even poorer, יביא עשירית האיפה, yavi
asiris ha'eifah, bring the tenth of the ephah flour, bring a מנחה.
mincha. הפריש עשירית האיפה, hifrish asiris ha'eifah, now that's reverse, you set
aside for the flour, העשיר, he'ashir, and you became richer, then יביא
עוף. yavi of. You don't get, you can't say, as Mike was
saying, oh it all goes by the moment you set it aside.
No. What's clear from this משנה Mishnah is that the moment we
determine your wealth is not the moment you sanctify it. It's a
different moment. We'll see what in the גמרא. Gemara. So if you
got richer you can't get off the hook by just bringing the
מנחה. mincha. You have now, you have to now bring a bird.
העשיר, he'ashir, if you're even richer than that, יביא כשב ושעירה, yavi
kesev u'se'irah, you have to bring the sheep and there it's more
obvious, you add money. So still the חידוש chidush is that you
can transfer קדושה kedusha from one to another, but it's not from
one חטאת chatas to a different חטאת, chatas, from one sin to
another sin or one person, same person, same sin, it's just one
type of animal to another, one type of or מנחה mincha to
an animal. That is the חידוש chidush or that's not considered redesignating
or, you know, that is a, you're allowed to make that shift.
And the other חידוש chidush is is that you can even do
it and pocket the difference. Of course if you're buying something more
expensive, it's not a חידוש chidush that you can add money, but
the חידוש chidush still is you can make the shift. Let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara. מנלן הני מילי, minalan hani milei,
where do we know this from? דתנו
רבנן. detanu rabanan. מחטאתו. me'chataso. Again back to the פסוק pasuk of
מחטאתו. me'chataso. Okay. מחטאתו על חטאתו. me'chataso al chataso. Now when by
when it speaks about the עולה ויורד, oleh ve'yored, it says the
following. It says when it says that you bring the sheep or
when it says you bring the bird, it says you shall bring
this animal מחטאתו, me'chataso, from your sin. Michael can read the exact
פסוק. pasuk. When it says you bring the עשירית האיפה, asiris ha'eifah,
the מנחה, mincha, it says you bring this פסוק pasuk על חטאתו,
al chataso, on your sin. And the דרשה derasha is going to
be the following. מם mem means from. It's a subset of the
larger amount. So what it's going to read is you set aside
money for the sheep or the goat, you will bring, you can
also bring מחטאתו, me'chataso, you can also bring a חטאת chatas from
that larger amount. Not the entire larger amount, but a subset of
that. So if you set aside for the sheep or the goat,
you can also bring if you become poorer you can bring less
than that. If you set aside for the for the bird, you
can bring מחטאתו. me'chataso. If you become poorer, you can bring some
of that, not all of that. If you set aside for the
מנחה, mincha, then it's also possible you can bring על חטאתו, al
chataso, you can add to the מנחה mincha and bring a higher
amount. So you get it, the מם mem means less, a subset,
telling you that if you need to you can move down on
the scale if you get poorer. The על al means on top
of, more than, and that's telling you if you get richer you
move up on the scale and you have to add to it.
Okay. So let's take a look. מה תלמוד לומר, mah talmud lomar,
what does it teach you? מנין להאומר שמביאין מהקדש כשב לשעירה ומהקדש
שעירה לכשב, minayin l'omer shemevi'in mehekdesh kesev lise'irah u'mehekdesh se'irah l'kesev, first
how do you know you can switch even within a category from
a sheep to a goat and a goat to a sheep? Again,
this is the money, not the actual
animal, once again also sanctified. and how do you know you can
go ahead and go down if you have to, if you got
poorer, to the bird? ומהקדש תור ובני יונה עשירית האיפה u'mehekdesh tor
u'vney yonah asirit ha'eiphah and go down from the bird to the
מנחה. mincha. כיצד. keitzad. הפריש כבשה או שעירה והעני יביא עוף. hifrish
kisbah o se'irah vehe'ani yavi of. So if you set aside for
the כבשה kisbah and goat and you got poorer you can bring
birds. והעני vehe'ani poor, יביא עשירית האיפה, yavi asirit ha'eiphah, you bring
the tenth of the איפה eiphah flour. הפריש עשירית האיפה hifrish asirit
ha'eiphah or the reverse, if you do the tenth of the flour,
והעשיר vehe'ashir you got richer, יביא עוף, yavi of, then you bring
the bird. והעשיר vehe'ashir you get richer, יביא כבשה או שעירה yavi
kisbah o se'irah you bring a sheep or goat. הפריש כבשה או
שעירה ונסתאבו. hifrish kisbah o se'irah venista'evu. Now let's say you set
aside a sheep or goat and they got a blemish. אם רצה
יביא בדמיהן עוף, im ratzah yavi bidmeihen of, meaning not only can
you move down if you have money set aside, even if you
have an animal set aside, when you're allowed to remove the קדושה
kedushah from the animal you can also go down. When are you
allowed to if you get poorer, when are you allowed to remove
the קדושה kedushah from the animal? If it has a blemish. So
obviously once the animal's sanctified you're stuck, but if it has a
blemish and you're now going to transfer it, how do I know
the same rule applies that if you got poorer you're allowed to
move down the scale? הפריש
עוף ונסתאב, hifrish of venista'ev, you did a bird and it got
a blemish, לא יביא בדמיו עשירית האיפה. lo yavi bidmav asirit ha'eiphah.
Ah, we weren't expecting that. You can't go from a bird to
a מנחה. mincha. Why? Anybody know up from the ר"ן? Ran? Because
the הלכה halachah is there's no פדיון pidyon by birds. Okay, so
therefore you're stuck if it's a bird. You can't redeem and you
sanctified the bird even with a blemish you cannot redeem it. שאין
לעוף פדיון she'ein le'of pidyon and because a bird doesn't have redemption.
Anyway, but the basic point is the one problem of sanctifying the
bird itself, so how do you know you when you need to
you move up and down the
scale? לכך נאמר מחטאתו על חטאתו. lekach ne'emar meichatato al chatato. מחטאתו
meichatato means when you have to take less and move down you're
allowed to move down. על al means when you move up you're
required to move up. ואיצטריך למיכתב מחטאתו ve'itztrich lemichtav meichatato גבי כבשה
או שעירה, gabi kisbah o se'irah, it has to say it by
the case of the sheep and the goat. ואיצטריך למיכתב ve'itztrich lemichtav
גבי עוף, gabi of, and it also has to repeat it by
the bird. Why couldn't it just say from one? You can move
down from the sheep to the bird and then I would have
inferred you can continue to move down the ladder? No, דאי כתב
קרא de'i katav kra גבי הקדש כבשה או שעירה, gabi hekdesh kisbah
o se'irah, had it just said it by the sheep or the
goat, הוה אמינא hava amina הפריש כבשה כי מעני מחלינן מעות נחתינהו
hifrish kisbah ki me'ani mahalinan me'os nachitinhu על עוף, al of, I
would have said fine, if you set it aside for the sheep,
then when you got poorer you can transfer this money על עוף
al of to a bird. ומייתי עוף, u'maytei of, and then you
can bring a bird. דכבשה ועוף תרווייהו מיני דמים נינהו, de'kisbah ve'of
tarvaihu minei damim ninhu, at least they're both animals, they both have
blood on the altar, same basically conceptual type of atonement, putting blood
on the altar. So to move from birds to, from sheep to
birds is still generally within the same category. אבל עשירית האיפה, aval
asirit ha'eiphah, but to go from birds to a מנחה, mincha, דלאו
מיני דמים נינהו, de'lav minei damim ninhu, it's not about blood, it's
a completely different type of a קרבן. korban. אי לאו כתב מחטאתו
iy lav katav meichatato גבי עוף, gabi of, had it not said
מחטאתו meichatato by the bird, then it did not say it again
you can't go from bird to מנחה. mincha. הוה אמינא, hava amina,
I would have said, כי מפריש מעות לקינו, ki mafrish me'os le'kino,
when you set aside money for a bird, ומעני ve'me'ani and you
get poorer, לא מייתי עשירית האיפה, lo maytei asirit ha'eiphah, you cannot
go down the scale. דלאו מיני דמים נינהו, de'lav minei damim ninhu,
it's, this language is clearly a little repetitive. Anyway, it's not types
of bloods and therefore you can't move down the scale. אלא מייתי
עשירית האיפה מביתו, ela maytei asirit ha'eiphah mi'beiteih, you'll have to go
ahead and bring your מנחה mincha from your own house. והלין מעות
דהפריש יפלו לנדבה. ve'halin me'os de'hafrish yiplu linedavah. Now what is it
going to say? If you can't use the money from the bird,
you can't go down the scale, you have to bring the, the
money for the bird goes for a נדבה nedavah and you have
to
bring the מנחה mincha yourself. I would have thought that. Interesting, right?
That's what you would assume. You already sanctified the money, you're out
the money. Interestingly, it assumes that although the idea of moving you
down the scale is to be lenient for you, if you are
in the category of super poor, actually you don't bring a bird,
because a super poor person doesn't bring the bird, you have to
bring a מנחה, mincha, and therefore you have to put out more
of your own
money to bring the מנחה. mincha. And the money you sanctified for
a bird, what are you going to do with it? So what
do you do with money sanctified for a חטאת chatat that can't
be used for a חטאת? chatat? Well, it's not actually a live
חטאת, chatat, it's just money. So the הלכה halachah is that it
goes for a נדבה, nedavah, it gets brought for an עולה. olah.
So you can't even bring the bird if you wanted to, that's
the irony. The Torah allowed you to move down the scale, but
it really didn't give you an option. It said, once you're in
this category, this is your קרבן, korban, which is, I guess, I
admit, quite ironic. Okay. So why say על חטאתו al chatato by
the כבשה kisbah then?
What? Why does it say על חטאתו al chatato for the כבשה
kisbah then?
All right, we're not דורש darshening the על חטאתו al chatato by
the כבשה. kisbah. All right, so anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says,
so in that case, so again that's quite fascinating. יפלו, yiplu,
הכי הדר כתיב קרא מחטאתו. hachi hadar ketiv kra meichatato. So anyway,
that's what I would have thought, that you go ahead and you
have to bring an עשירית האיפה asirit ha'eiphah and you cannot because
you're not allowed to use the money to move down, you can't
go from bird to מנחה, mincha, and you have to bring the,
the money for the bird goes for an עולה olah and you
have to bring the מנחה mincha yourself. I would have thought that.
הכי הדר כתיב קרא מחטאתו hachi hadar ketiv kra meichatato גבי עוף.
gabi of. Therefore it says it by birds as well that you
can move down. You move down. דאמר מר דהמקדיש עוף נמי מייתי
עשירית האיפה, deamar mar dehamakdish of nami maysi asiris haeifa, even money
set aside for the birds, even though they're different types of קרבנות,
Korbanot, you can move from the birds to the מנחה, Mincha, you
are allowed to move down the scale. You do not bring both,
right, and you move down the scale. והכי קאמר, vehachi kaamar, this
is what the פסוק Pasuk is telling you, כי מפריש עשירית האיפה,
ki mafrish asiris haeifa, if you set aside,
I'm sorry, no, it's missing a phrase. And this is now going
to the פסוק Pasuk of על חטאתו. al chatato. Okay, ואצטריך למכתב
על חטאתו veitztrich lemichtav al chatato by the way. So that's why
it has to say מחטאתו, mechattaso, you move down the scale even
if you're going from birds to a מנחה, Mincha, different types of
a קרבן. Korban. Now it says על חטאתו, al chatato, you move
up the scale. והכי קאמר, vehachi kaamar, and this is what it's
saying: כי מפריש עשירית האיפה, ki mafrish asiris haeifa, you set aside
the money for a מנחה, Mincha, ואחר כך העשיר, veachar kach heashir,
and before you brought it you got richer, מוסיף עליהם, mosif aleihem,
you have to add to it, ומייתי עוף, umaysi of, and bring
a bird. העשיר, Heashir, you got richer, מוסיף עליהם, mosif aleihem, you
add to it, ומייתי כשב או שעיר, umaysi kisbah o seirah, you
bring a sheep or a goat. מאי טעמא כתיב על חטאתו mai
taama kesiv al chatato גבי עשירית האיפה? gabei asiris haeifa? So why
did it write that by the עשירית האיפה asiris haeifa to say
you move up? Why not say it, I don't know, by the
bird that you can move up to the sheep? דאי כתב על
חטאתו גבי עוף, dei kesav al chatato gabei of, had it said
it by the middle category, the bird, הוה אמינא, hava amina, I
would have said the same point. כי מפריש מעות לקינו והעשיר הוא
דמוסיף עליהן ומייתי כשב או שעיר, ki mafrish maos lekino veheashir hu
demosif aleihen umaysi kisbah o seirah, when you set aside for birds
and got richer, then you move up to the sheep or the
goat. Why? Because it's still fundamentally the same category, דמין דמים נינהו,
demin damim ninhu, it's all about blood. אבל הפריש מעות לעשירית האיפה,
aval hifrish maos leasiris haeifa, if you set it aside for the
מנחה, Mincha, והעשיר, veheashir, and you got richer, אי לא העשיר טובא
מייתי עוף, אם העשיר טובא מייתי כשב או שעיר, i lo heashir
tuba maysi of, im heashir tuba maysi kisbah o seirah,
I would say fine, if you got not super rich, medium rich,
whatever, you know, you would bring a bird; super rich, you would
bring a כשב Kisbah or שעירה. Seirah. Obviously you have to bring
the higher level, but I might not think you can use the
מנחה Mincha money, because maybe מנחה Mincha money is different than animal
money. And therefore again, what would you have to do with that?
תולין מעות שהפריש יפלו לנדבה, tolin maos shehifrish yiplu linedavah, so the
money that you had for the מנחה, Mincha, that would all turn
into a freewill type of a money, go for some other קרבן,
Korban, and all of your thing would be out of pocket. So
if I didn't know you could move up, the same way if
I didn't know you could move down, I would think the money
is stuck in that designation. You can't use it for your קרבן,
Korban, whether it's more expensive or less expensive. It's not your right
category. You can't use it. All your קרבן Korban has to be
out of pocket. That money has to go for some other purpose.
I would have thought that, and I would have thought you cannot
go from מנחה Mincha to bird.
והכי כתיב קרא בדאית חטאת בעשירות ודלות מחטאתו, vehachi kesiv kra bedais
chattas beashirus vedallus mechattaso, so therefore it had to say everything. By
the wealthy and the medium amount, it had to say מחטאתו mechattaso
to tell you you can move down and reuse that money for
the lower on the scale. וגבי דלי דלות על חטאתו, vegabei dalli
dallus al chatato, by the super poor, על חטאתו al chatato to
tell you you move up even though you're going from מנחה Mincha
to animals. למדרש כדאמרן, lemidrash kidamran, in order to interpret it as
we have said. Again, this is quite verbose for the גמרא, Gemara,
but anyway, it's nice and very clear, helps us get through the
דף Daf pretty quickly.
Okay, so basically I
understand, Michael, you'll have to look somewhere else for the answer to
that. So anyway, that's to tell you that although you can't switch
from one person to another, one חטאת Chatat to another, when it's
an עולה ויורד, Ola VeYored, you can move within, you know, that
קרבן Korban for what its purpose is, from what type of קרבן
Korban you're bringing. Okay. אמר רב אלעזר אמר רבי אושעיא, Amar Rav
Elazar amar Rabbi Oshaya, מטמא מקדש וקדשיו, metamei mikdash vekodashav, somebody who
was טמא Tamei who entered into the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash or
ate קדשים, Kodashim, which is one of the classic עולה ויורד Ola
VeYored categories.
עשיר, Ashir, now you were rich when you did this. שהפריש קן
לכבשתו. shehifrish kan lechivsato.
So you went ahead and you set aside birds instead of your
כשב, Kisbah, meaning you're supposed to
have brought a כשב—כשבה, כבשה, Kivsah, same thing. Okay, anyway, so you
were supposed to have brought a sheep because you were rich, but
you set aside the money and you said, I'm going to bring
birds, okay? Or actually you actually set aside the birds themselves, which
was not your קרבן. Korban. Your קרבן Korban was the more expensive
one. So what do we say about him?
הואיל ונדחה ידחה. hoil venidcha yidacha. Excuse me, והעני. veheani. And now,
so you set aside the birds themselves. Now you actually got poorer.
Serves you right. Okay, so, sorry, you can't use the birds. Why
not? I've already sanctified them, they're my right קרבן Korban now. No.
הואיל ונדחה ידחה. hoil venidcha yidacha. They were pushed away, they remain
pushed away. When you were rich, these were not your allowed קרבן.
Korban. You could not have brought these; if you had brought them,
you wouldn't have been יוצא. yotzei. These were not acceptable for your
קרבן Korban when you were rich. So they were said non-acceptable. When
they were labeled non-acceptable, this is בעצם דחוי, beetzem dichuy, they were
stigmatized at that time and they remain therefore not acceptable even though
now they are your right קרבן. Korban. Now, it's not money, right?
Money, that's actually an interesting question, because money you're allowed to change,
that's when you set aside the right money. What if you set
aside the wrong money? You know, although you say maybe moneys are
fungible, it's harder to say right money or wrong money. So it
would be an interesting question whether we would say the same if
you set aside the money for birds. But if you're actually setting
aside the birds themselves, that's a non-acceptable קרבן Korban right now and
therefore it remains pushed away. Yes.
Do these birds have קדושה? Kedusha?
Sure. There's קדושת דמים וקדושת הגוף. kedushas damim u'kedushas haguf. Exactly. Exactly.
Therefore it's not right. The whole point of דיחוי dichuy really only
occurs once something has קדושה. kedushah.
That's an even bigger penalty because you can't even use the birds.
Right. Exactly. Exactly. You have to wait till it gets a מום
mum and then transfer—well actually you can't transfer because birds don't have
פדיון. pidyon. So you're like, you're really stuck with those. Okay, so
אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, Amar Rav Huna breih deRav Yehoshua,
what are we saying?
No, because they were set—they had קדושת חטאת. kedushat chatat. And a
חטאת chatat that now cannot be קרב. karev. So you're really stuck
with those for the rest of time.
So the poor person becomes very poor and it can't
be—that was money, so money can be transferred but the actual animal
itself, right, that can't be unless you could פודה podeh it but
you can't be פודה podeh birds. Okay. אמר רב הונא בריה דרב
יהושע Amar Rav Huna breih deRav Yehoshua שמע מינה תלת. shema mina
telat. So whenever the גמרא Gemara deals with דיחוי dichuy it always
gets into a שמע מינה תלת. shema mina telat. This is a
slightly different three than it had last time. שמע מינה בעלי חיים
נדחין, shema mina ba'alei chayim nidchin, it's pushed away even though it's
a live animal. Some say that can't happen. וקדושת דמים נדחה, u'kedushat
damim nidcha, even though when it was originally sanctified it was never
fit for being brought as a קרבן. korban. At the moment it
was sanctified it was not fit, which means it was only a
קדושת דמים. kedushat damim. And therefore I would have thought that maybe
if it's never fit it would not be considered נדחה. nidcheh. No,
even if it only started with קדושת דמים kedushat damim that's considered
stigmatized and pushed away. And also בדיחוי מעיקרא הוי דיחוי, vedichuy mei'ikara
havei dichuy, even if that's again saying if it was never fit
it was you know it was pushed away from the very beginning.
Different than having been fit and then rejected. Never fit, maybe once
it becomes fit it will be acceptable. No, even דיחוי מעיקרא dichuy
mei'ikara is a problem. Now of course דיחוי מעיקרא dichuy mei'ikara sounds
to be the exact same thing as קדושת דמים. kedushat damim. If
something was נדחה מעיקרא nidcha mei'ikara then the whole קדושה kedushah it
got was never קדושת הגוף, kedushat haguf, it was only קדושת דמים.
kedushat damim. There's often very large תוספות'ס Tosafots that explain it, but
really the real answer is that the גמרא Gemara always wants threes
and the last two here are always very similar when it does—not
always, but always when it does it in the case of בעלי
חיים נדחין. ba'alei chayim nidchin. The first one is always בעלי חיים
נדחין, ba'alei chayim nidchin, the last two are more or less the
same in order to get three. Okay, anyway. That's—but that's a thing
that we've heard before. Now, מתיב רב עוקבא בר חמא. metiv Rav
Ukva bar Chama. So this was the statement that if you set
aside the birds they are—remain rejected. So רב עוקבא בר חמא Rav
Ukva bar Chama asked המפריש נקבה לפסחו hamaprish nekeivah le'pischah קודם הפסח.
kodem haPesach. Somebody set aside a female sheep or goat for the
פסח Pesach and it was before פסח. Pesach. Obviously pretty much any
time is before פסח. Pesach. Anyway, but the רש"י Rashi says that
phrase was a little extra. So he set aside a female. So
you can't bring it, the פסח Pesach is a male. What do
you do? תרעה עד שתסתאב ותמכר ויביא בדמי הפסח. tir'eh ad shetista'ev
vetimacher veyavi bidmei haPesach. You wait for it to get a blemish,
you transfer the money and then you use the proceeds to buy
a פסח. Pesach. Fine. A male. ילדה זכר, yaldah zachar, it gave
birth to a male, this female, before you redeemed it. ירעה עד
שיסתאב וימכר ויביא בדמי הפסח. yireh ad sheyista'ev veyimmacher veyavi bidmei haPesach.
You can't use the male itself. It's not the original קדושת פסח.
kedushat Pesach. It's only derived from an animal that has קדושה—but kedushah
the קדושת פסח, kedushat Pesach, but the mother, the source of the
קדושה kedushah was not a קדושה kedushah that could be קרב. karev.
So the offspring also does not have a קדושה kedushah to be
able to be brought and therefore you have to wait to transfer
the value. רבי שמעון אומר Rabbi Shimon omer לא, הוא עצמו יקרב
פסח. lo, hu atzmo yikarev Pesach. That it itself can be brought
as a פסח Pesach even though the mother cannot. That's not—doesn't really
like affect the קדושה. kedushah. It's still קדושת פסח kedushat Pesach and
therefore the child that is male can be brought. שמע מינה shema
mina from רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon we see בעלי חיים אינן נדחין,
ba'alei chayim einan nidchin, that בעלי חיים ba'alei chayim are not נדחין.
nidchin. Because if the mother's status was considered נדחה, nidcheh, נדחה nidcheh
really means like you know like invalidated,
stigmatized, invalidated and so on, then clearly a קדושת דיחוי kedushat dichuy
would not have enabled to make the child you know brought. So
he obviously says you can't bring the mother because the mother's a
female and so on and that's not acceptable for a פסח, Pesach,
but that does not make it considered נדחה, nidcheh,
stigmatized, invalidated and so on. And therefore the child which is male
can be brought. So that goes against you.
You see, alright, let's take a look. אמר בי רב יאשיה, Amar
bei Rav Yoshiyah, so the בי רב יאשיה bei Rav Yoshiyah said
no, כי אמרינן לרבנן דרבי שמעון. ki amrinan le'rabbanan de'Rabbi Shimon. Fine,
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says it's not נדחה. nidcheh. What, like we
haven't heard until now that there's a whole debate? We have to
say שמע מינה בעלי חיים נדחין. shema mina ba'alei chayim nidchin. It
clearly proves that this is an issue that is contested and debated.
So fine, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says it's not נדחה. nidcheh. I
was talking according to the rabbis who argue on רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon. They סבירא ליה—ורבי שמעון סבירא ליה, savira lei excuse me I
put the comma the wrong place. כי אמרינן לרבנן, ki amrinan le'rabbanan,
I was talking about the rabbis. ורבי שמעון סבירא ליה בעלי חיים
אינן נדחין. ve'Rabbi Shimon savira lei ba'alei chayim einan nidchin. Fine, רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon we know holds that בעלי חיים ba'alei chayim are
not נדחין. nidchin. But who says we agree with רבי שמעון? Rabbi
Shimon? Now how do we know he says that? Because he also
says he says that והגרלה אינה מעכבת. ve'hagralah einah me'akkevet. And he
also says—and we're going to see both of these brought up in
the same case—that the drawing of the lots on the goats of
יום כיפור Yom Kippur is not מעכב. me'akkev. Even if you didn't
draw lots it still works. And we'll see both of these in
the following case. דתניא detanya we taught in a ברייתא. braita. מת
אחד מהן, met echad mehen, one of the pair you drew the
lots on the goats and one of them died. So what do
you do, right? You have to bring another goat. Now as we
know, we've seen this before, some people say you bring two goats,
you draw the lots, the one that got the missing one gets
paired up and the other one you'll figure out what to do
with. Okay, but you would do the normal assumption is you have
to take two goats and draw lots again, which is
הגרלה. hagralah. Forget the lots thing now. You just bring one other
goat and you pair it up. You don't need to do the
lots if you're in this stuck situation. So he says number one,
lots is not מעכב me'akev for יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. But what
he also says is בעלי חיים אין נדחין, ba'alei chayim ein nidchin,
that for until you got its pair, this remaining live goat was
not usable, right? Because until you paired it up, it was stuck.
And nevertheless, that does not make it נדחה, nidche, invalidated, and in
a way that it's sort of stuck and cannot be used again.
Does he need to take one of like a twin for that?
Yeah, everybody says take a twin. But some people say you can't
even take a twin because בעלי חיים נדחין. ba'alei chayim nidchin. He
says number one, you can't take a twin, בעלי חיים אין נדחין,
ba'alei chayim ein nidchin, it could become reused. And number two, you
don't even need to draw lots. אלמא קסבר, alma kasavar, you see
he holds בעלי חיים אין נדחין. ba'alei chayim ein nidachim. Number one,
it's not pushed away, the live one does not get rejected. And
number two, הגרלה אינה מעכבת. hagralah einah me'akeves. If you don't, if
you're not able to or whatever, it doesn't make sense, you don't
even have to draw the lot. Okay, so fine, yeah, there's a
רב שמעון. Reb Shimon. We don't, I don't hold of רב שמעון.
Reb Shimon. Obviously this issue is contested. Alright. So that was interesting
when you set aside not money but the actual birds themselves, if
they're not in your right category, they remain rejected. Now the גמרא
Gemara continues. אמר רב חסדא: Amar Rav Chisda: אין הקינין מתפרשות אלא
או בלקיחת בעלים או בעשיית כהן. ein hakinim mispareshos ella o bilkichas
ba'alim o ba'asiyas kohen. Now
this line is going to probably be the dominant theme when we
get to מסכת קינין, Masechet Kinnim, which is not too far away,
only a month away, supposed to be the hardest מסכת masechet in
ש"ס, Shas, but we only have משניות. Mishnayos. I don't know if
that makes it better or worse. Anyway, the הלכה halacha of קינין,
Kinnim, a lot of that case is you take, you know, you're
obligated in a קרבן korban of birds, which is normally one is
a חטאת, chatas, one is an עולה, olah, and the whole case
is like all these permutations that you take them and they get
mixed up with other birds, and which is which? And how do
you find which is the חטאת, chatas, which is the עולה? olah?
Anyway, so one of the key principles, that's the whole מסכת masechet
that we'll get to, one of the key principles is that these
birds, when do they, when can they be designated, which is a
חטאת, chatas, which is an עולה? olah? And the key statement for
this is the statement of רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. There are two
moments where they could be designated: either when you purchase them, okay,
you purchase the birds, you're the owner, and you say, this is
going to be the חטאת, chatas, this will be the עולה, olah,
or when the כהן kohen actually does the עבודה avodah on the
birds and he says which is the חטאת, chatas, which is the
עולה. olah. But if you didn't designate them at the time you
bought them, any designation you do afterwards is meaningless. They remain generic
חטאת chatas עולה, olah, they remain generic your קן, kan, your sort
of cluster of birds, your nest, and they only can get designated
either at the moment you purchase or when the כהן kohen does
it, no time in between. Okay, so that's what he says. Let's
take a look. אין הקינין מתפרשות, ein hakinim mispareshos, they do not
get designated, אלא או בלקיחת בעלים, ella o bilkichas ba'alim, either when
the owner's purchase it, או בעשיית כהן, o ba'asiyas kohen, or when
the כהן kohen actually brings it as a קרבן. korban. אמר רב
שימי בר אשי: Amar Rav Shimi bar Ashi: מאי טעמיה דרב חסדא?
mai ta'amei de-Rav Chisda? What's his reasoning? דכתיב, de-ksiv, the פסוק pasuk
says: ולקחה שתי תורים, ve-lakcha shtei sorim, the woman who's חייב chayav
in this קרבן, korban, I think it's יולדת, yoledes, takes two birds,
and then it says אחד לחטאת ואחד לעולה. echad le-chatas ve-echad le-olah.
So that idea, one for חטאת, chatas, one for עולה, olah, is
at the moment of ולקחה, ve-lakcha, when she purchases it. So either
the purchasing is when it's designated, and the other פסוק pasuk says
ועשה הכהן, ve-asah ha-kohen, the כהן kohen shall make them, אחד לחטאת
ואחד לעולה. echad le-chatas ve-echad le-olah. So the phrase, אחד, echad, one
for חטאת, chatas, one for עולה olah occurs when it's purchased or
when it's done by the כהן, kohen, when it's brought, and nowhere
in between does it get assigned.
Okay. או בלקיחת בעלים או בעשיית כהן, o bilkichas ba'alim o ba'asiyas
kohen, one or the other. מיתיבי, Meisvei, I'll ask you on this:
ועשהו חטאת, ve-asao chatas, הגורל עושהו חטאת. hagoral oseo chatas. Now, so
this seems to be why we got into this discussion now. I
mean on number one, our משנה Mishnah was talking about birds and
number two we just quoted the הגרלה hagralah case of יום כיפור.
Yom Kippur. So by יום כיפור Yom Kippur as well there's an
idea of non-defined which is which and then getting defined, right? You
have two goats, which is which? So it's a sort of analogous.
And how does it get defined? When you pull the lot, ועשהו
חטאת, ve-asao chatas, then you designate which is לעזאזל la-Azazel and which
is the חטאת. chatas. הגורל עושהו חטאת, hagoral oseo chatas, only the
drawing of the lot, says the ברייתא, brayasa, determines which goat is
which, which is לעזאזל la-Azazel and which is the חטאת. chatas. ואין
השם עושהו חטאת, ve-ein ha-shem oseo chatas, if you just verbally said,
this is a חטאת, chatas, that doesn't do it. It's not the
calling out of the שם, shem, it's the actual lot. ואין כהן
עושהו חטאת, ve-ein kohen oseo chatas, or the כהן kohen presumably also
by verbal designation or other forms, nobody, no component of this does
it, not the כהן, kohen, not the calling out of names, you
need the actual
lot. שיכול לומר, she-yachol lomar, if so I'd feel it's logical to
say that those things work. ומה במקום שלא קידש הגורל, קידש השם,
u-mah bimkom shelo kiddash hagoral, kiddash hashem, by a normal קרבן, korban,
how do you sanctify a קרבן? korban? If I did a lot
by a קרבן korban and I pulled it and told it over
an animal, that wouldn't make it a חטאת. chatas. Right, if I
took an animal I want to make it a חטאת, chatas, I
have to be verbally מקדיש makdish it and say it's a חטאת.
chatas. So a normal קרבן korban gets its sanctity and its identity
through verbal הקדשה, hakdasha, through שם shem and not through drawing of
lot. So I could have made a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. Why
would it have said like this? ומה במקום שלא קידש הגורל u-mah
bimkom shelo kiddash hagoral by a normal קרבן korban lot would not...
sanctify my animal. קידש השם kidesha shem and the verbal sanctification does
it, מקום שיקדש הגורל makom sheyakidesh hagoral the place like by the
two goats of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, where the drawing of a
lot, we know creates the sanctity. אינו דין שיקדש השם eino din
sheyakadesh hashem how much more so should it be true that my
verbal designation should be able to designate? תלמוד לומר talmud lomar so
the verse says, ועשהו חטאת, ve'asahu chata'as, it shall make it somehow
I don't know where the מיעוט miyut is but anyway, it shall
make it a חטאת. chata'as. גורל עושה חטאת goral oseh chata'as only
the lot, ואין השם עושה חטאת ve'ein hashem oseh chata'as no verbal
designation. By the, by these it is only the name. Of course
you've already sanctified the animals, the question is just which is which.
It's not like a normal type of a קרבן korban where you
need your verbal designation to sanctify. Here you have verbally sanctified it,
but which is which is defined by the drawing of lots. Okay,
anyway.
קתני שם דומיא דגורל. ktani shem dumya degoral. Now we're going to
analyze this ברייתא. braisa. So we talked about the designation similar to
the drawing of lots. מה גורל לאו בתחילת בעלים ויציאת כהן, ma
goral lav bit'chilas ba'alim veyatzias kohein, now when does the drawing of
lots occur? They don't occur when the animals were purchased, they don't
occur when they were shechted, they occur some middle stage between being
purchased and being shechted. So therefore and we're saying and we're comparing
that to designation, verbal designation, that suggests that verbal designation can occur
after purchase. אף השם נמי לאו בתחילת בעלים ויציאה af hashem nami
lav bit'chilas ba'alim veyatzia it suggests that that can occur not at
the moment of doing or of buying or at the moment of
doing. Now of course why the גמרא gemara didn't answer we're talking
about normal animals and sanctifying them and we're not talking about the
whole special case of the birds is not clear but presumably actually
maybe the גמרא gemara understands that we דווקא davka should be talking
about birds because that's the thing it's most similar to, right? Because
both by birds and by the goats you already sanctified them and
the question is just which is which. So if we're going to
make an analogy it should be to birds and here it sounds
like we're comparing so if we're comparing the lot to the designation
so the lots don't occur at the time of purchase maybe the
designation also doesn't have to. So that sounds like that the designation
can occur at a different time. So אמר רב amar Rav or
רבא הכי קאמר. Rava hachi ka'amar. No here's the comparison. It's an
analogy, it's not the direct same-same. ומה במקום שלא קידש הגורל בלקיחת
בעלים וביציאת
כהן, uma bimkom shelo kidesh hagoral bitlechisas ba'alim uveyatzias kohein, when it
comes to birds, so we're going to assume we're talking about birds,
the lots would not work at the right time. What's the right
time for birds? When they're purchased or when the כהן kohein shechts
it or does מליקה. melika. So at the right time for birds
lots do not work, nevertheless קידש השם kidesh hashem either בלקיחת בעלים
וביציאת
כהן, bitlechisas ba'alim uveyatzias kohein, verbal designation does work for birds at
the right time. So כאן שיקדש הגורל שלא בלקיחה שלא ביציאה, kan
sheyakidesh hagoral shelo bitlechisa shelo veyatzia, here where lots work at their
time which is not purchase and not doing but some middle time,
but lots work by the goats at their time, אינו דין שיקדש
השם eino din sheyakadesh hashem either בלקיחה וביציאה bitlechisa uveyatzia so certainly
verbal designation should have worked at this time? תלמוד לומר ועשהו חטאת
הגורל עושה חטאת ואין השם עושה חטאת, talmud lomar ve'asahu chata'as hagoral
oseh chata'as ve'ein hashem oseh chata'as, only the lot not the designation.
So the point is it's not the same thing, it's an analogy.
You're right we are comparing the goats to the birds, again those
are the most similar, they've already been sanctified the question is which
is which, okay, but we're not saying that just because the goat
time is some middle time we're assuming the birds is some middle
time. What we're saying is look by the birds whenever is the
right time for it to work, it works verbally, it doesn't work
with a גורל. goral. Whatever that right time is. By the birds
the right time happens to be purchase or the כהן. kohein. But
whatever that right time is it works verbally. Here not by lot.
Here where it's right time which is a different time works by
lot how much more so should it work by verbal designation? So
we're not identifying the times but we're making an analogy and it
uses a פסוק pasuk to say not. Okay, so now the גמרא
gemara goes on. מיתיבי, meiseiv, I'll still challenge this idea about the
time of designation. Again it's a little funny what this is doing
here maybe because of as I said the tie-in to the goats
maybe because our משנה mishna is about switching designations you know from
up and down and so on so this is also a form
of designation when this is established.
Okay, מיתיבי, meiseiv, I'll ask you again on this, נטמא מקדש עני
שהפריש מעות לקינו והעשיר, nitamei mikdash ani shehifrisha me'os le'kino vehishir,
and here's where it actually,
oh I'm sorry, here it's explicit why we're bringing it in because
of this line in the משנה. mishna. Okay, so somebody that was
poor that set aside money and then got rich and then became
richer, ואחרי כך אמר אלו לחטאתי ואלו לעולתי, ve'acharei kach amar elu
lechata'asi ve'elu le'olasi,
so this is a similar it's a ברייתא, braisa, it's not our
משנה, mishna, but it's on the same theme. So what did you
do? You set aside money for your birds and then now that
you are rich, now you're rich you can't be bringing birds. You
have to be bringing your sheep or goat, okay, and that's the
whole point, that since you are no longer in the category of
bringing birds anything you say about this money and how they're going
to be used is irrelevant at this stage in fact as far
as birds are concerned because you're no longer in a position to
bring birds. And then you say after you got rich I'm going
to use this money
for the חטאת chatas and this amount of it for the עולה.
ola. מוסיף mosif maybe so then but now it seems like it
does stick, it does work. So what happens? מוסיף ומביא חובתו מדמי
חטאתו mosif umeivi chovaso midemei chataso the amount of the that you
said for the bird money would be used for your חטאת. chatas.
Now you have to bring a goat חטאת chatas or sheep חטאת,
chatas, so you take that חטאת chatas part of the money, you
add to it, and you bring your goat or your sheep.
ואין מוסיף ומביא חטאתו מדמי עולתו, ve’ein mosif umeivi chataso midemei olaso,
and you can't go ahead and use the money that of that
part of the pie you said would be for an עולה olah
because once it's designated as the עולה, olah, then it's stuck. So
now this is actually, shows us why we brought this in here,
and shows how it fits with the משנה. Mishna. The משנה Mishna
says you take the bird money and you add to it. This
ברייתא braisa is clarifying that's only if that money has not been
sort of subdivided and designated, it's generic bird money. But once it's
subdivided, and this חטאת chatas bird and עולה olah bird money, you
only can add to the חטאת chatas money and use it for
your sheep or goat. The עולה olah money has to remain as
an עולה olah because you're not bringing a חטאת, chatas, rather you're
not bringing an עולה. olah. The only time you bring an עולה
olah is when you bring the bird, but when you bring the
sheep or goat you only bring a חטאת, chatas, so you can
only add to the חטאת chatas for your sheep or goat, then
you bring the עולה olah then as a נדבה. nedavah. Okay, so
that's the חידוש chiddush there that from adding to the bird money,
it's only when it has, the entire amount is only when it
has not been subdivided. So the גמרא Gemara says, ואין מוסיף ומביא
חובתו מדמי עולתו, ve'ein mosif umeivi chovaso midemei olaso, הכא hacha
here דליכא לקיחה ולא עשייה, deleka lekichah velo assiyah, it wasn't the
time of purchase and it wasn't the time of the שחיטה, shechitah,
you just had a pile of money sitting in front of you.
And nevertheless, you are subdividing it, וקתני מביא חובתו מדמי חטאתו ולא
מדמי עולתו. ukatanei meivi chovaso midemei chataso velo midemei olaso. Your designation
of which is the חטאת chatas part and which is the עולה
olah part works, even though it was not an earlier time of
the earliest time or the latest time. אמר רב ששת ותסברא, Amar
Rav Sheshes usisbara, says, does it make sense? מתניתא מתקנתא היא masnisa
metakanta hi that our, that that ברייתא braisa is a good text?
מתניתא משבשתא היא, masnisa meshabeshta hi, that ברייתא braisa is a bad
text. How do I know? דקתני והעשיר dekatanei ve'he'ashir because the ברייתא
braisa says after you got rich, ואחר כך אמר, ve'achar kach amar,
after you got rich, you said this part is for the חובה,
chovah, this part is for the עולה. olah. So how can you
say which is for what after you're rich? It's no longer relevant
here, you're no longer in the bird category. ואמר רב אלעזר אמר
רבי אושעיא, Ve'amar Rav Elazar amar Rabbi Oshaya, Rav Elazar says in
the name of Rabbi Oshaya, מטמא מקדש עשיר שהביא קרבן עני לא
יצא, metamei mikdash ashir she'heivi korban ani lo yatza, that if you
were to try, even בדיעבד, bedi'eved, if you brought the bird, you
would not be יצא. yotza. That was implicit by the way before
also where we said that if you set aside a bird it's
נדחה. nidcheh. Okay, so בדיעבד bedi'eved it doesn't work. So if you
are completely out of the bird category right now, how, why are
you in a position to say which is for the עולה olah
which is for the חטאת? chatas? This is an irrelevant קרבן korban
for you right now. So the ברייתא braisa doesn't make sense because
it sounds like your designation works after you became rich and that
shouldn't be true. אלא מאי אית לך למימר, Ella mai is lach
lemeimar, how would you have to interpret the ברייתא? braisa? שכבר אמר,
she'kevar amar, when it says you got rich and you said this
is עולה olah this is חטאת, chatas, it doesn't mean you said
it after you got rich, it means you had already designated which
was for the עולה olah which was for the חטאת. chatas. Okay,
so meaning his point is if you're rich, how do you have
a right to say which is for what, your bird isn't relevant
to you? So the phrase in the משנה Mishna in the ברייתא
braisa that says you said which is which doesn't mean you said
it after you got rich, it means you had already said. Once
it means you had already said it, so שכבר אמר משעת עניותו,
she'kevar amar misha’as aniyuso, you had already said it when you were
poor, הכי נמי שכבר אמר משעת הפרשתו, hachi nami she'kevar amar misha’as
hafrashaso, so your whole challenge to me was how could you designate
which is which after you've set aside the money. So since anyway
the ברייתא braisa has to mean that you had in the past
said which is which, I'll say that when did you say which
is which? When you originally set out the money. It didn't mean
you first set it out, it was a generic pile and then
you subdivided it. I'll interpret the case that you had originally said
this is my חטאת chatas money, this is my עולה olah money,
so it's like the way you can designate when you buy the
bird, you can also designate when you initially sanctify the money. Alright,
so is that clear, meaning this is a ברייתא, braisa, this makes
it clear, I'm sorry what I said before, this makes it clear
why we're bringing this in here. The ברייתא braisa clarifies the משנה.
Mishna. You can only add to the bird money if it's non-specified.
Once it's specified, you can only add to the חטאת, chatas, the
עולה olah have to remain an עולה. olah. And here it sounds
like though that you can designate which is which after you set
aside the money. And he says no, from this ברייתא braisa anyway
you have to say it means that you designated it earlier because
you certainly have to designate it before you get rich. So therefore
what it means is you designated it from the very beginning. Yes.
Even implicitly there was some money in the pile for the עולה
olah you used the whole thing?
Yes, until it is designated it has just a generic identity. It's
not like there is חטאת chatas and there is עולה olah money
and you don't know which is which. It still has a sort
of like generic identity. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. Okay. ולרב חגא
אמר רב אושעיא דאמר יצא, U'leRav Chaga amar Rav Oshaya de'amar yatza,
מאי איכא למימר? mai ika lemeimar? Now your whole proof that the
ברייתא braisa was meant you had done it originally was because you
said that once you're rich, a bird sacrifice cannot work for you
even בדיעבד. bedi'eved. And again that was similar to before that we
said the bird was נדחה. nidcheh. But there actually is a position
of רב חגא אמר רב אושעיא Rav Chaga amar Rav Oshaya that
says בדיעבד, bedi'eved, if you took something at the wrong place on
the scale, you are יצא. yatza. Even a rich person that brought
a bird בדיעבד bedi'eved would be יצא. yatza. So according to him
it could really mean you designated after you got rich because you
still are relevant to a bird קרבן korban and therefore there's no
proof that the ברייתא braisa means... you originally did it. So גמרא
Gemara says תני ואחר כך לקח, tani ve-achar kach lakach, no, nevertheless,
I will, you'll still have to read it that it says, oh,
so when it says, oh, so for him I will read it
that when did you designate, not when you, not that you took
the money and you separated it out and designated, that would not
be the right time, but you took the money and you purchased
the bird. So there really are two times you can designate how
the money is being used for according to this idea. Either when
you originally sanctified the money, you can say this is חטאת, chatas,
this is עולה, olah, or if you then sanctified and took the
money and bought the bird, at the moment of buying, which is
what we've been saying or the כהן kohen does it, but as
we've been saying, we've been saying the moment of buying. Now we
introduce that if you put aside money, it could also be the
moment the money's put aside. But that doesn't eliminate the moment of
buying. So this ברייתא braisa that said that you designate, and if
we read it to mean you designated later, which is which, the
later will be the moment of purchase and that will be able
to work. But along the way we have seen that there's an
interesting debate whether בדיעבד bedieved you could bring a bird and whether
therefore if you could, that puts you in a position to designate
which is which because it still would remain relevant to you.
Okay. מיתיבי, masvei, I'll ask on this, מצורע עני שהביא קרבן עשיר
יצא. metzora ani she-heivi korban ashir yatza. So here we have a
ברייתא braisa that says that if you go up on the scale,
you're poor and you bring a richer one you're יוצא, yotzei, which
by the way goes back to our משנה mishna or whatever the
earlier discussion that maybe even if you were stuck with birds you
should go ahead and bring it. Anyway but that's בדיעבד. bedieved. עשיר
שהביא קרבן עני לא יצא, ashir she-heivi korban ani lo yatza, if
you went down on the scale, לא יצא, lo yatza, which makes
a lot of sense. The Torah is going easy on you, but
if you therefore if you want to bring a more expensive one
you're יוצא, yotzei, a less expensive you're not. תיובתא דרב חגא אמר
רב אושעיא. tyuvta de-rav chaga amar rav oshaya. So that's now we're
onto this new point about we've moving on beyond when do you
designate the birds, and we're asking, can you bring down the scale?
So this ברייתא braisa is explicit you cannot bring lower on the
scale, that's a contradiction to the position that you can.
אמר לך, amar lach, no, שאני גבי מצורע. shani gabi metzora. That
case where you can't go down the scale, did I skip a
line?
No. No, I did. מצורע עני, metzora ani, I did skip a
line.
Okay, ואמר, ve-amar, okay, מיתיבי, masvei, I'll ask you, מצורע עני שהביא
קרבן עשיר יצא. metzora ani she-heivi korban ashir yatza. עשיר, ashir, דידי,
de-dai, no I didn't. Did I? One minute.
Just start from the top whatever since I'm not sure where we
are on and right now.
Okay, מיתיבי. masvei. We're going to start from three, six lines down,
about five words in. מיתיבי. masvei. Let's try again.
מצורע עני שהביא קרבן עשיר יצא. metzora ani she-heivi korban ashir yatza.
Now, it's a מצורע. metzora. Okay, that that, now by מצורע metzora
as well, the Torah shows a scale based on how much you
can afford. So the ברייתא braisa is about a מצורע. metzora. A
poor מצורע metzora that brought a higher, brought a higher expense קרבן
korban higher up on the
scale, he's fulfilled. עשיר שהביא קרבן עני לא יצא. ashir she-heivi korban
ani lo yatza. If you brought down he's not יוצא. yotzei. I
just think I didn't translate the word מצורע. metzora. We're talking specifically
that a מצורע metzora can go up on the scale but not
down. תיובתא דרב חגא אמר רב אושעיא. tyuvta de-rav chaga amar rav
oshaya. It's a contradiction of רב חגא Rav Chaga אמר amar רב
אושעיא Rav Oshaya because it said that בדיעבד bedieved you could go
down on the scale, and here it says a מצורע metzora cannot
go down on the scale בדיעבד. bedieved. אמר לך, amar lach, he'll
tell you, no, שאני גבי מצורע. shani gabi metzora. By מצורע metzora
there the Torah is explicit that you cannot go down. How do
you know? דמיעט רחמנא זאת, de-mi-it rachmana zos, this is the law
of the מצורע, metzora, to tell you it's exactly this way and
therefore you cannot go down. אי הכי, ei hachi, if that's true,
it's exactly this way, אפילו מצורע עני נמי שהביא קרבן עשיר לא
יצא, afilu metzora ani nami she-heivi korban ashir lo yatza, then you
shouldn't be able to go up either if it's exactly this way.
So גמרא Gemara says לאי, la'ay, why, why would you say that?
הא הדר קרא, ha-hadar krah, the Torah goes back and expands the
category. תורת, Toras, it says זאת תורת, zos toras, this is the
law. So law generally means like it's broad and inclusive, זאת zos
means it's exact. So we have one thing that says it has
to be exactly this way, the other says not so much. So
which does it, so how would I translate that? Obviously exactly means
you can't cheat and go down, not so exact means but you
can spend more and go up. Okay. והא תניא, ve-ha tanya, we
turn a ברייתא, braisa, תורת לרבות מצורע עני שהביא קרבן עשיר יצא.
torat le-rabos metzora ani she-heivi korban ashir yatza.
That תורת toras is inclusive, says if you're poor and you bring
an expensive one you're
יוצא. yotzei. יכול אפילו עשיר שהביא קרבן עני שיצא, yachol afilu ashir
she-heivi korban ani she-yatza, maybe even if you go down on the
scale you're יוצא, yotzei, תלמוד לומר זאת, talmud lomar zos, this. Okay.
So by מצורע metzora we learn from the פסוק pasuk that you
can go up on the scale but not down. ולילף מיניה, ve-le-ilaf
minei, why not learn from it? That you can never be, that
you can never go down. Why do you say that by a
normal עולה ויורד oleh ve-yored בדיעבד bedieved if you go down you're
יוצא? yotzei? אמר קרא ואם דל הוא ואין ידו משגת. amar krah
ve-im dal hu ve-ein yado maseges.
So and if he's poor and his hand does not reach, מצורע
הוא דעשיר שהביא קרבן עני הוא דלא יצא. metzora hu de-ashir she-heivi
korban ani hu de-lo yatza.
By the מצורע metzora that's where the Torah says that if you,
that if you go down you're not יוצא yotzei because it says
ואם דל הוא, ve-im dal hu, like this case only applies to
this case, הוא hu is a limiting word. This case, if you're,
you know, you have to only if you're poor can you bring
a poorer one. The הוא hu is limiting, only by the מצורע.
metzora. But it says by, where did I slip the line, אבל
מטמאי מקדש עשיר שהביא קרבן עני יצא. aval mitamei mikdash ashir she-heivi
korban ani yatza.
I would not apply that to other cases, there I would say
if the Torah gives you a couple of options, you have to
logically assume that any one could count
as for-by-for, okay, בדיעבד. bedieved. So and by the way it seems
from this That everybody would agree that בדיעבד bedi'eved if you brought
a more expensive one you're יוצא. yotze. It seems, we don't know,
maybe not. Maybe the one that says בדיעבד bedi'eved it doesn't work
down, maybe it'll also say בדיעבד bedi'eved it doesn't work up. But
it sounds like going up maybe everybody agrees, and everybody agrees by
מסורה mesorah you can't go down. The question is בדיעבד bedi'eved if
you went down by עולה ויורד, oleh veyored, and you can understand
the debate. On the one hand the תורה Torah tells you what
קרבן korban to bring, you do what the תורה Torah says. On
the other hand, since it's giving you a couple of options based
on your wealth, presumably it's arguable that any one of them בדיעבד
bedi'eved is a valid קרבן. korban. So that is the debate by
עולה ויורד. oleh veyored.
Last משנה, mishnah, that was what, the very poor person who
brought a bird?
Yeah, exactly. בדיעבד. bedi'eved. But the question is at what stage? בדיעבד.
bedi'eved.
That was to רבא, Rava, whatever? Yeah, but the others wouldn't disagree.
Like going down they would disagree, it's not clear if they would
disagree going up. Okay. רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, last משנה
mishnah of the מסכת. masechet. רבי שמעון אומר כבשים קודמין. Rabbi Shimon
omer: kevassim kodmin. Now that we're talking about switching sheep, goats, whatever,
okay, and we said you could switch from sheep to goats, well
is there a preference sheep or goats? Like, you know, clearly we
know more expensive, less expensive, how about between sheep and goats? So
כבשים קודמין לעיזים בכל מקום. kevassim kodmin l'izim bechol makom. Anytime the
תורה Torah mentions sheep and goat, it always mentions sheep first. Okay.
יכול מפני שמובחרין מהם, yachol mipnei shemuvcharin mehem, maybe because they're choice,
they're better, and you should prefer sheep over goats? תלמוד לומר ואם
כבש יביא קרבנו לחטאת. talmud lomar: v'im keves yavi korbano lechatat.
In one place the תורה Torah spoke about first bringing a goat
and then said and if you bring a sheep. So in one
place it reversed it. מלמד ששניהם שקולין, melamed sheshneihem shkulin,
that they're really all the same. Okay, it says it normally there's
a stock phrase sheep and goats, but really they're equivalent and therefore
it reversed in one place. It's like sometimes רשי Rashi sometimes in
the תורה Torah quotes the idea, you know, that it's always משה
Moshe comes before אהרן Aharon but sometimes one of the times it
mentions אהרן Aharon before משה Moshe to tell you that they're all
equivalent. Okay. תורין קודמין לבני יונה בכל מקום. torin kodmin livnei yonah
bechol makom. Whenever the תורה Torah mentions תור tor and בני יונה,
vnei yonah, it mentions תור tor first. יכול מפני שמובחרין מהם, yachol
mipnei shemuvcharin mehem, maybe because they're the choice? תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar,
so in one place it says, you know, the גרסא girsa has
to be switched here, ובן יונה או תור לחטאת. u'ven yonah o
tor lechatat. Okay,
מלמד, melamed, so there it says בן יונה ben yonah first, ששניהם
שקולין, sheshneihem shkulin, that it reversed the order in one place to
tell you they're all really the same. האב קודם לאם בכל מקום.
ha'av kodem l'em bechol makom. The father normally comes before the mother
when the תורה Torah mentions it, like כבד את אביך ואת אמך.
kabed et avicha v'et imecha.
So יכול מפני שכיבוד אב קודם לכיבוד אם, yachol mipnei shekibbud av
kodem l'kibbud em, maybe to tell you that there's a precedence to
the honor one shows to his father than to his mother? תלמוד
לומר איש אמו ואביו תיראו. talmud lomar: ish imo v'aviv tira'u.
So in one place the תורה Torah reverses it and mentions the
mother first. מלמד. melamed. I know, but this משנה mishnah normally, right,
רשי Rashi as in the whole תורה Torah emphasizes why the תורה
Torah emphasizes one for כיבוד kibbud and one for יראה, yira, but
this isn't what this משנה mishnah is doing. This משנה mishnah is
telling you that it reversed it to tell you not to make
a, not to give a priority for that. So מלמד ששניהם שקולין,
melamed sheshneihem shkulin, that they're both equal. אבל, aval, רבקה, Rivka, here
this is for you.
אבל אמרו חכמים, aval amru chachamim, but there's rabbis said, האב קודם
לאם בכל מקום. ha'av kodem l'em bechol makom.
Nevertheless, the father comes before the mother. Why? מפני שהוא ואמו חייבים
בכיבוד אביו. mipnei she'hu v'imo chayavim bikibbud aviv.
Because he and his mother have to honor the father. Which says
that it is not the father's responsibility to honor his wife, it's
the wife's responsibility to honor the husband, which is actually not true
because we actually say that the husband's responsibility is to honor his
wife. You know, the famous line in the גמרא Gemara is אוהב
אשתו כגופו ומכבדה יותר מגופו. ohev ishto k'gufo u'mechabdo yoter migufo.
So it's actually interesting here that it frames it as though it's
only the wife's responsibility to honor the husband, not the reverse. And
therefore if a child has to choose from both parents, he listens
to the father because the mother to some degree according to this
משנה mishnah has to also defer to the father. But this would
not be true, it does not contradict because it would not be
true if they're divorced or if they are not married, right? So
in that type of a case father and mother have equal, have
you know, there's not a hierarchy in terms of the child honoring
father or mother. The hierarchy only exists if the mother's in a
state of also being the father's wife. Okay, so רבקה, Rivka, I
know there's a lot to react to that, but we have to
finish in the next two minutes or we won't be able to.
וכן בתלמוד תורה, v'chen b'talmud torah, similarly by תלמוד תורה, talmud torah,
אם זכה הבן לפני הרב, im zachah haben lifnei harav,
if the child is meritous and is, you know, is able to
study תורה Torah in front of a רב, rav, הרב קודם את
האב בכל מקום. harav kodem et ha'av bechol makom. You actually have
to give honor to the, to the רב rav over the father.
Why? Is it because fundamentally honor to תורה Torah precedes honor to
the parent? Maybe
not, but מפני שהוא ואביו חייבים בכבוד רבו. mipnei she'hu v'aviv chayavim
bichvod rabo. Now there are other places where it actually says that
in principle the greater כבוד kavod is demanded for the רב rav
than for the father because זה הביאו לחיי העולם הזה וזה הביאו
לחיי העולם הבא. zeh hevio l'chayei ha'olam hazeh v'zeh hevio l'chayei ha'olam
haba. Here it seems to be saying that it's really a different
reason. It's because even the one that you, the father himself is
obligated in honor to the, to the רב rav and that gives
the רב, rav, that means the רב rav has to be deferred
to in the case of conflicts of תורה. Torah. You know, it
makes it different. תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan. Okay, so those last two
lines which are clearly the most fascinating. are not going to be
discussed now. One gets more analysis in קידושין, Kiddushin, the other more
in הוריות. Horayot. We will now wrap up. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabanan:
ארבע צווחות צווחה עזרה. Arba tzvoach tzavcha azara. Four crying outs the
temple courtyard cried out. צווחה אחת הוציאו מכאן בני עלי חופני ופנחס.
Tzvacha achas hotziu mikan benei Eli Hofni uPhinehas. Get out from here
the sons of Eli, Hofni and Phinehas, שטימאו את ההיכל, shetimu es
haheichal, that they impurified the היכל. Heichal. We know their stories in
תנ"ך. Tanakh. So it's basically saying, you know, it's personifying the עזרה
Azara and it's sort of saying like get them out of here,
they don't belong here. צווחה שנייה, Tzvacha shniya, the second one,
פתחו שערים ויכנס יוחנן בן נדבאי תלמידו של פינקאי, pitchu shari veyikanes
Yochanan ben Nidbai talmido shel Pinkai, whoever he was, but let this
כהן Kohen come in, he does a good job here. Why? וימלא
כריסו, veyemalei kreiso, now it's interesting, the phrase, and fill his belly,
מקדשי שמים, mikodshei shamayim, from the sacrifices of heaven. אמרו על בן
נדבאי שהיה אוכל ארבע סאה גוזלות, Amru al ben Nidbai shehaya ochel
arba se'ah gozalot, he would eat
four סאה se'ah of birds, which is an enormous amount, בקינוח סעודה,
bekinuach seuda, just for dessert. Okay, so you would think that this
guy is disgusting, like, you know, he's a glutton, but nevertheless, here's
why it was a good thing that he was around. אמרו כל
ימיו לא היה נותר
בעזרה. Amru kol yamav lo haya notar ba'azara. As long as he
was around, there was never meat left over, you always knew he
would eat it up. Alright, which is interesting because you would still
wonder whether he was always doing it לשם שמים. leshem shamayim. Anyway,
צווחה שלישית, tzvacha shelishis, the
third crying out, שאו שערים ראשיכם ויכנס אלישמע בן פיכאי תלמידו של
פנחס, su shear roshechem veyikanes Elishama ben Phikai talmido shel Pinchas, okay,
so not clear who that was, but it clearly was a תלמיד
talmid of פנחס, Pinchas, some say ישמעאל, Yishmael, not אלישמע. Elishama. Anyway,
וישמש בכהונה גדולה, veyishamesh bikehuna gedola, let him be כהן גדול. Kohen
Gadol. No comment on that. צווחה רביעית, Tzvacha revia'is, פתחו שערים והוציאו
יששכר איש כפר ברקאי, pitchu shearim vehotziu Issachar ish Kfar Barkai, get
rid of this guy יששכר איש כפר ברקאי, Issachar ish Kfar Barkai,
שמכבד עצמו, shemechabed atzmo, here it is not like the guy who
ate a lot, maybe that was done in the proper way, but
here he's so focused on his own
honor, ומבזה קדשי שמים, umeraze kadshei shamayim, he shows disrespect, denigrates the
sacrifices. מאי הוה עביד, Mai hava avid, what did he do to
take care of his honor at the expense of the sacrifices? הוה
כריך שיראי על ידיה, Hava kareich shirei al yadei, he would wrap
his hands in some type of like silk, he put on silk
gloves, והוה עביד עבודה, vehava avid avoda, and he would do the
עבודה, avoda, he didn't want to get his hands dirty. Okay, so
he was so concerned about his כבוד kavod he didn't want to
get his hands dirty, and that פסול pasuls the עבודה, avoda, because
if you're not touching it directly, it's
פסול. pasul. מאי סליקא ליה, Mai selika lei, what was his, you
know, end, what did he get ultimately as a result of
these actions? ינאי מלכא ומלכתא הוו יתבין, Yannai malka umalkesa havi yasvin,
so ינאי Yannai the king and the queen, his wife, were sitting.
מלכא אמר גדייא יאי, Malka amar gadaya ya'ei, the king said
goats are best.
מלכתא אמרה אימרא יאי, Malkesa amra imra ya'ei, no sheep are best.
אמרו נשייליה ליששכר איש כפר ברקאי דכהן גדול הוא ואיכא ליה קדירה,
Amru nishayelei le-Issachar ish Kfar Barkai dekohen gadol hu veika lei kedeira,
he's always in front of a pot, or some have a different
גרסא, girsa, but he's always there with the קרבנות, korbanos, he knows
which are best. Question whether they're talking about which taste best, which
are best for קרבנות, korbanos, anyway, let's ask him. שאלוהו, Sha'alui, they
asked him.
אמר
להו אם גדייא יאי יסיק ליה תמידא, Amar lei im gadaya ya'ei
ya'aseik lei tamida, so he said to them rather, he said, if
goats were better, they should have been brought for the קרבן תמיד,
korban tamid, so clearly since the sheep are brought every single day
for the קרבן תמיד, korban tamid, it's clear that sheep are better,
which is not so smart because he's siding with the queen, not
the king. Okay, so בהדי דקאמר אחוי בידיה, bahadi de'amar achvi biyadei,
and as he was saying,
he sort of like made a dismissive gesture with his hand. He
said, if sheep were better, you know, goats were better, why weren't
they brought as a קרבן תמיד? korban tamid? So not only did
he side with the queen, but he made a dismissive gesture towards
the king. אמר להו מלכא, Amar lehoun malka, so the king said
to his servants, הוא דאחוי בידיה, hu de'achvi biyadei, since he made
this dismissive gesture with his hands, קצצו לידיה ימינא, katze'u leyadei yemina,
let his right hand be cut off, which obviously will mean he,
he put his hands in silk gloves to take care of his
hands whether he was doing the עבודה, avoda, now his hand is
going to get cut off and he won't be able to do
the
עבודה. avoda. יהב שוחדא, Yahiv shochda, so
he gave a bribe to the guy who was supposed to execute
the sentence, קצצו לידיה דשמאלא, katze'u leyadei schmola, they only cut off
his left hand, not his right hand. שמע מלכא, Shama malka, the
king heard, אמר וקצו נמי לידיה דמינא, amar vekatzu nami leyadei yemina,
so now we still gotta cut off the right hand, because that's
what I said. So he got both his hands cut off. אמר
רב יוסף ברוך רחמנא דשקליה ליששכר איש כפר
ברקאי למטפסריה. Amar Rav Yosef baruch rachmana deshaklei le-Issachar ish Kfar Barkai
lemetafsarei. Praise is God that יששכר איש כפר ברקאי Issachar ish Kfar
Barkai got למטפסריה, metafsarei, it's a question what that word means, but
it probably means his comeuppance. Okay, which is a nice word for
if that's what it means. He thank God that he got his
comeuppance. Now, it seems a little cruel he got his hands cut
off, but you know, in terms of teaching people you don't fool
around with, you know, you don't take care of your own honor
over the honor of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. אמר רב אשי
ולא הוה תני ליה. Amar Rav Ashi velo havi sani lei. He
not only that, he never learned משניות. Mishnayos. דתנן כבשים קודמים לעיזים
בכל מקום. Detnan kivasim kodmim le'izim bechol makom. יכול מפני שמובחרים תלמוד
לומר ואם כבש מלמד ששניהם שקולים. Yachol mipnei shemuvcharim, talmud lomar ve'im
keves, melamed shesheneihem shekulim. Our משנה Mishnah says that they are equal
because one place reverses it. כך רבינא אמר אפילו מקרא נמי לא
קרא, Kach Ravina amar afilu mikra nami lo kara, he didn't even
know פסוקים, Pesukim, דכתיב אם כבש אם עז, dikesiv im keves im
ez, that the way it's phrased, if a sheep, if a goat,
that is very parallel. language to emphasize that they are completely equivalent.
So not only was he taking care of his own honor, he
was an עם הארץ *am ha'aretz*. So we got to get in
the last insult.
Okay, because he said all those mean things and now we also
maybe showed some תלמידי חכמים *talmidei chachamim* with a little bit of
a little destructive tendency, we end to counterbalance it. אמר רבי אלעזר
אמר רבי חנינא תלמידי חכמים מרבים שלום בעולם *Amar Rebbe Elazar amar
Rebbe Chanina talmidei chachamim marbim shalom ba'olam*. In the end if you're
a תלמיד חכם *talmid chacham* it leads to peace, שנאמר וכל בניך
למודי ה׳ ורב שלום בניך *shene'emar vechol banayich limudei Hashem verav shalom
banayich*, אל תקרי בניך אלא בוניך *al tikrei banayich ela bonayich*. Not
exactly clear how that ties in. Maybe to counter the previous story,
maybe also to tie in from the last line of the משנה
*Mishnah* about כיבוד רב *kibbud rav* and the importance of תלמוד תורה
*talmud torah* leading to שלום *shalom*. הדרן עלך מסכת פסחים וסליקא לך
מסכת פסחים *Hadran alach masechet psachim v'silka lach masechet psachim*. Okay.